<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Disputation proving that it is not convenient to grant unto ministers secular jurisdiction, and to make them lords &amp; statesmen in Parliament</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 94 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36143</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1677</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15032</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12542702</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12542702</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62994</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36143)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62994)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 313:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Disputation proving that it is not convenient to grant unto ministers secular jurisdiction, and to make them lords &amp; statesmen in Parliament</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Bishops --  Temporal power.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament. --  House of Lords.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62994:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62994:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISPUTATION: PROVING, That it is not convenient to grant UNTO MINISTERS SECULAR JURISDICTION; And to make them Lords &amp; Stateſmen IN PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year MDCLXXIX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:62994:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:62994:2"/>
            <head>It is not expedient to grant unto Clergy-men ſecular Juriſdiction.</head>
            <p n="1">1. I Do not undertake to prove that it is ſimply unlawful: And the worthy and judicious Biſhop <hi>Davenant</hi> doth grant and aſſert,<note place="margin">Determ. queſt. 11.</note> That the Law of Prudence and Equity it ſelf doth forbid Kings to burden Clergy-men with it, ſo far as it will let and avocate them from their ſpriritual office and function.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It will be demanded who muſt be Judge what is, and what is not expedient? To which the forenamed <hi>Davenant</hi> makes anſwer, That is to be accounted expedient which a Wiſe Man ſhall ſo judge and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine: whereunto I aſſent. He afterwards adds, That which a wiſe and religious Prince ſhall ſo determine. Neither do I diſſent in this, provided it be ſoundly underſtood: For that which a wiſe and religious Prince ſhall judge to be expedient, if it be ſo indeed, all wiſe men will, at leaſt they ought ſo to think; for ſound wiſdom is the ſame in all: But it is too poſſible for the moſt wiſe and prudent Prince to enjoyn things not good and expedient. King <hi>David</hi> thought it moſt prudent to number the people, who was a moſt wiſe Prince; but in that his wiſdom fail'd him. <hi>Joab,</hi> his General, that was much inferiour to <hi>David</hi> in goodneſs and heavenly wiſdom, thought it very imprudent: and the event proved <hi>Joab</hi> to be the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer man in that.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Some things are more evidently, other things are leſs evidently expedient: The Scales may hang ſo even and equilibrious, that a wiſe comparing judgment can ſcarce tell whether is the heavier end, and whether part hath the ſtronger reaſons: and the Scales may be ſo odd and unequal, ſo much ſolid reaſon may be ſaid for the one ſide, and ſo little for the other, that to a wiſe comparing judgment the caſe is not doubtful to decide. Now I ſhall manifeſt, that it is evidently inexpedient to grant ſecular juriſdiction to Miniſters and Glergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that is, That the ſame perſon be a Miniſter, Biſhop or Paſtor of Souls, and a Magiſtrate or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lve Judge, one that heareth the Sword, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:62994:3"/> 4. <hi>Arg.</hi> 1. Jeſus Chriſt did not ſee it meet to exerciſe any ſuch power while he was upon earth; being moved to be a kind of worldly. Judg between two Brethren, he refuſed, ſaying, <hi>Who made me a Judg or a divider over you?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Determ. quaeſt. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> Luk. 12.14. As if he ſhould ſay, (ſays <hi>Dave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> upon the words) Neither by divine nor by humane Ordination do I exerciſe Judiciary power over private perſons, much leſs over Kings: By which argument the ſame <hi>Davenant</hi> goes about to prove the nullity of the Popes power in Temporals. Now if his argument be of force againſt the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> I ſee not but it is of equal force againſt worldly Juriſdiction in all Biſhops and Paſtors whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever. Now if Chriſt ſaw it not meet for him to exerciſe worldly Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, methinks all Biſhops and Paſtors of Souls, who have their office and calling particularly from him, ſhould ſee it meet to learn of him and imitate him herein, and Princes themſelves ſhould not think it expedient to burden Miniſters with that, which Chriſt himſelf re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed and put from him as either unlawful in it ſelf, or inexpedient: <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.29, <hi>Take my yoke upon you, and learn of me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Arg.</hi> 2. The Apoſtles and the ſucceſſors of the Apoſtles, the Biſhops and Paſtors of the Churches for the ſpace of three hundred years unto the time of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> had no Temporal Juriſdiction, nor did exerciſe any. And thoſe are counted the beſt and pureſt times of the Church. If we may not make the Apoſtles of Chriſt, and their immediate ſucceſſors the Biſhops and Paſtors of the Churches for the firſt three hundred years, our pattern, what ſhall we make our pattern, and by what law and rule ſhall we determine what is, and what is not expedient? Can we better govern our ſelves and the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches than they? Have we more wiſdom to invent and find out ways of good governing the Church than they had? Have we more holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and goodneſs, and faithfulneſs to God, our ſelves, our calling, and the Church, than had they? If the Church did well and beſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, when it had no Magiſtrates but what were Pagan, Infidel, and <hi>Jewiſh,</hi> many of whom were great Perſecutors, all of them de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> of the Chriſtian name; will it not well and better ſubſiſt, if better can be, where Magiſtrates are Chriſtian, and deſenders of the Faith, if Biſhops and Paſtors contenting themſelves with no more but the Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal and Paſtoral office, and refuſing all worldly Juriſdiction, ſhall wiſely and faithfully behave themſelves in their office, as thoſe firſt and moſt ancient Biſhops and Paſtors of the Churches did?</p>
            <p n="6">6. Unto this the worthy <hi>Davenant</hi> makes anſwer, That thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nes and ours are not alike. Thoſe times were exceeding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and good,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62994:3"/>ours be exceeding bad. There needed no ſecular authority in Paſtors then, there was ſo much holineſs and piety, the Word and Diſcipline were abundantly enough; but now the Chriſtian World is ſo excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding corrupt and degenerate, that unleſs Miniſters be armed with Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Juriſdiction, their authority will be deſpiſed, and the Diſcipline which God hath appointed to be in his Church, will be ſcorned as baſe and contemptible, rather than be reverenced for any good it will do; <hi>Non tam uſui eſſet, quam ludibrio,</hi> thoſe are his very words. <hi>Dave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> is the man whom I do highly eſteem, and ſo do all that be wiſe and knowing in the things of God: but in this <hi>Davenant</hi> hath fallen much below himſelf; and the feebleneſs of his reaſoning doth much confirm me in my judgment and perſwaſion, that the cauſe which he oppugneth, and which I do here defend, is too ſtrong to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown.</p>
            <p n="7">7. His anſwer is partly not true, not to ſay it is directly and flatly falſe: For let any impartial man make a due eſtimate of things, and compare the Paſtors and Churches under the Apoſtles (I except the perſons of the Apoſtles themſelves) and during their abode upon earth, and their ſucceſſors the Paſtors and Churches immediately following to the time of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> I ſay compare theſe with the Paſtors and Churches of our times, and it will be found that there is no ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equality as he ſuggeſts. <hi>Bradford</hi> and <hi>Philpot,</hi> and <hi>Rogers,</hi> and <hi>Cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> and <hi>Latimer,</hi> and <hi>Ridley,</hi> and <hi>Hooper,</hi> and <hi>Bilney,</hi> and <hi>Sanders,</hi> and other of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Martyrs were worthy and famous Martyrs of Chriſt, as well as were thoſe firſt and moſt ancient Martyrs. And <hi>Grindal,</hi> and <hi>Jewel,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> and <hi>Davenant,</hi> and <hi>Gataker,</hi> and <hi>Vines,</hi> and <hi>Hildeſham,</hi> and <hi>Preston,</hi> and <hi>Sibbs,</hi> and <hi>Dod,</hi> and <hi>Joſeph Allen,</hi> and many more of our own and foreign Divines were able to vye with the ancient Biſhops and Paſtors of the Churches, ſuch as died not Martyrs. And the private Chriſtians, and Families, and Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations of our times, are not much inferiour to thoſe ancient ones both <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin,</hi> and even to thoſe we have mention of in the New Teſtament, namely the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> thoſe of <hi>Galatia,</hi> and <hi>Judea,</hi> that at <hi>Corinth</hi> and others.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Admit it were true, which queſtionleſs is not: I ſhould rather think that the way to reduce an unreformed Church and people from hereſie and unholineſs, to foundneſs in the faith and holineſs, is for Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors to content themſelves with the work of Paſtors, and give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves wholly to it, and ſuffer no lets. Will the Sword convert ſouls, or awe mens conſciences? would it likely do more good if a Miniſter
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62994:4"/>ſhould come into the Pulpit with a Sword in one hand, and a Bible in the other? The Sword is not appointed of God for the converſion of Souls; the office of the Magiſtrate is to make way for the work and office of the Miniſter. It is the ſword of the Spirit which is the Word of God, which muſt cut in pieces mens luſts, and breed in them ſound faith, holineſs, and reformation, and not the ſword of the Magiſtrate. Let the Magiſtrate do or not do his duty, let him be Pagan or Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor, and let the people be more loofe and unreformed than they are, let but Paſtors and Miniſters do their duty well, and we ſhall ſoon ſee that Gods Word and Diſcipline is of the ſame force now that ever it hath been; otherwiſe there is a change in God, and his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe fails, and Satan is ſtronger now than he hath been, and Chriſt and the Holy Ghoſt are much weaker. Read and conſider well theſe Scriptures, [<hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18, 19, 20. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Mich.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Iſa</hi> 45.19. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49 4, 5. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.58. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.11. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15, 16. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1, 2. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4, 5, 6.] to name no more, and let but Miniſters be wiſe and faithful, and try if it be not the beſt and ſpeedieſt way to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form what is amiſs in the Church, contenting themſelves with no more but their own office, and leaving all force and ſecular authority to the Magiſtrate.</p>
            <p n="9">9. If we be the ſame that the ancient Paſtors were, be ſure God and Gods Word will be the ſame; we cannot do Gods part, nor the Magiſtrates part, nor the peoples part, we can only do our own part; which we may do if we will; do our own part, and be ſure God will be with us and do his. What hinders but Paſtors may be as wiſe and holy as they have been of old? If we be not, it is our own fault. The more corrupt the times are, the more need Paſtors have to beſtir them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and to double their diligence, and lay out themſelves more vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorouſly, to be more Exemplary, to abound in the work of God, to be mortified, to loſe no time, to ſuffer no let. To make them Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, were to let them, and take away much of their time, and rather hinder and diſtract, than further them. If the Paſtors office he as much as they can wiſely and faithfully do, would it further them in their work to have another effice and work added to them? Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel are not ſo fit as others to be worldly coercive Judges and Secular Magiſtrates. For their office is purely Paſtoral, and is to have no terrour in, but the terrour of Gods Word, and ſpiritual denunciations, that the people may have no temptations to withdraw their love and eſteem from their Paſtors. A Thief at the Bar had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have a Miniſter than the Judg to reprove him, though both
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62994:4"/>ſhould pronounce the ſame truth, and hit upon the ſame words, and have equal wiſdom and integrity. For properly Magiſtrates are for outward terrour to evil doers, and for outward deſence and protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to them that do well, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.3. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.14. But Miniſters are to be gentle to ſouls, even as a nurſe cheriſheth her children, and to exhort and comfort, and charge every one as a father doth his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.7, 11. But if parents and nurſes, and tender mothers ſhould rule their children by the ſword too, that would not add to their office, nor further their work.</p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>Arg.</hi> 3. If it be ſo as <hi>Davenant</hi> ſays, that unleſs Miniſters be armed with Secular Juriſdiction, their office and authority in the Church, and the Lords Word and Diſcipline as adminiſtred by them, will be deſpiſed and trod upon; then neceſſarily all Miniſters ſhould be mad. Magiſtrates, and Princes are too blame if they do not put the ſword into all their hands, and make every Miniſter throughout the Nation a Juſtice of Peace, or a Sheriff, or a Judg, by giving him power to impriſon, and lay fines and penalties upon offenders, and to uſe coercive means. And then the Scriptures themſelves, even the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God will be found faulty, if he have ordained and appointed no ſuch thing in all the Bible, as I no where find that he hath done. And by the ſame reaſon Magiſtrates may ſay they alſo muſt be Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and there will be a confuſion of offices, and the bounds and banks of order in Church and Commonwealth will be thrown down; and if order be not oblerved, good government cannot be. For good government is nothing but the obſervance of right order; when Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates do the duty of Magiſtrates, and meddle with no more but what comes within the compaſs of their office, that is right order, and it breeds peace, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.33 40. And when Miniſters and Paſtors do their duty, and what properly pertains to their office, medling with no more, this alſo is right order, and the way of true and good government in the Church, and produceth peace. But if you leave this way and order, you err. And where your error may ſtop, and what miſchiefs and inconveniences it may produce, who is able to declare? For there is no ſafety but by keeping in Gods way, and cloſe walking by his rules <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>no abſurdo dato ſeq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>untur mille,</hi> is as true in Practicals as in Doctrinals.</p>
            <p n="11">11. <hi>A</hi> 4. Either Chriſtian faithful Magiſtrates are a help and defence to Gods Church, and to Miniſters in their calling and office, or they are not. If they are, then methinks if the Church and Miniſters did well when they wanted ſuch helps, they ſhould rather do better, at
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62994:5"/>leaſt they ſhould do as well, or not be much worſe, when they have ſuch helps. But to ſay they cannot do at all, or that Miniſters and their Diſcipline, and Miniſtration barely without Secular Juriſdiction added to them, will be of no uſe, but rather a ſcorn and mockery un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Chriſtian Magiſtrates, is ſtark ſhame and reproach to all ſuch Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and they ſhould rather be caſt out of the Church as intoler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and as dung and dead unſavoury ſalt, than be made Magiſtrates. What ſhould they do Magiſtrates that are not able by all they can do to preſerve themſelves from ſordid ignominy and contempt? or if not this, it is an intolerable ſhame to all, excepting Miniſters, both Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates and people, that they ſhould be ſo extreamly wicked and graceleſs, neither fearing God, nor regarding men, as to deſpiſe and ſcorn all the wiſe and holy, and faithful Paſtors in the Church that are but meer Paſtors. According to this opinion one of theſe two wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſes and abſurdities will follow; either that all the Paſtors in the Church that are but meer Paſtors, are ſhamefully wicked and into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable, and moſt unworthy to be Paſtors; or that all beſides in the Church that are no Paſtors, Princes, Rulers and people are extreamly wicked, even ſcorners and contemners of Gods Miniſters, Worſhip, Word, Diſcipline and holy inſtitutions.</p>
            <p>If Chriſtian Magiſtrates and ſuch as be faithful, be not a help and defence to Gods Church and Miniſters in their office, then it is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction to deſire their office as an help and expedient to the Church, and that Miniſters might be armed with the authority of a Magiſtrate too. And then it is no bleſſing but rather a curſe to have faithful Kings, Princes and Magiſtrates; and then we ſhould not pray for them; and then it were all one to have Perſecutors as Protectors, <hi>Julian</hi> as <hi>Conſtantine, Nero, Diocleſian,</hi> Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> and bloody Popes and Tyrants, as <hi>Theodoſius, Joſias,</hi> Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and wiſe, and juſt, and faithful Governors.</p>
            <p n="12">12. <hi>Arg.</hi> 5. Either you would have Paſtors and their authority in the Church reverenced, or you would not. If you would have them reverenced, what muſt it be for? you would have the ſame man to be a Paſtor and a Magiſtrate, and ſo to be reverenced. Very good; if then the ſame man as Paſtor be baſe and vile, worthy of no reverence, how ſhall we do to reverence the ſame man as Magiſtrate? ſhall we ſay that the ſame man is worthy and unworthy, vile and honourable, faithful and unfaithful? will you ſay that he hath two ſouls, or two conſciences, one as a Paſtor, and ſo he is a worthleſs wretch, to be contemned of all; and the other as a Magiſtrate, and ſo he is honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62994:5"/>and to be had in eſteem by all? If the ſame man as Paſtor be damned, what ſhall become of the ſame man as Magiſtrate? If Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors be worthy men, all men will reverence and eſteem them; at leaſt God will, and all that be taught and inſtructed of God. Even an <hi>Herod</hi> will reverence a <hi>John Baptiſt.</hi> Wiſdom and Holineſs will be reverenced in all; and folly, and vice, and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ckedneſs, will be rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced in none. But eſpecially wiſdom and holineſs will be reverenced in Paſtors; and vice, and folly, and hypocriſie, and unfaithfulneſs, will be thought not ſo odious and unſavoury in any, as in Paſtors and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops. For it is of them eſpecially that God ſaith, <hi>Them that honour me, I will honour; and they that deſpiſe me, ſhall be lightly eſteemed,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30 If a Miniſter be truly worthy and honourable, he ſhall be honoured. All right eſteeming men, if there be any that fear God, and make conſcience of his commands, will reverence, <hi>and eſteem him very highly in love for his works ſake,</hi> 1 Theſ 5.12, 13. But if he be but the meer name and outſide of a Biſhop, if he be a <hi>Bonner,</hi> a hater and perſecutor of good men, fooliſh, wicked, ambitious, ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, worldly, ſelf-ſeeking, contentious, heretical, ignorant, ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous and unfaithful, nothing that you can do will uphold his reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: make him a Lord or Prince in Parliament, heap all the dignities and honours that be among men upon him, make him the greateſt men for office in the Kingdom, next to the King himſelf, his vices a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d corruptions will ſhame him before the world; no covers forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, and worldly eminencies and additaments, will be able to hide the ſpots and deformitie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of his ſoul, and win him reputation with any but Fools, Flatterers and Knaves. For <hi>it is righteouſneſs, and it only, which exalteth a nation or perſon; but ſin is a reproach to any perſon or people,</hi> Prov. 14.34.</p>
            <p>If you would not have Miniſters and their authority in the Church reverenced and eſteemed, then you contradict your ſelves, who would have Miniſters to have worldly juriſdiction, as a means to procure them reverence and eſteem in the Church: and then it is no ſin not to eſteem thoſe that be worthy of eſteem; and then <hi>Judas</hi> and <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> be a-like worthy, and we are to be as thankful for, and rejoice in an <hi>Arrius</hi> as an <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> a <hi>Bonner</hi> as a <hi>Bradford,</hi> an Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian murdering wicked Pope, as a <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> and the moſt holy Paſtor and Biſhop upon earth.</p>
            <p n="13">13. <hi>Arg.</hi> 6. In defence of Miniſters being made Magiſtrates, ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry inſtances out of the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> be urged, which be of Gods or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining. As we read of <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> King of <hi>Salem,</hi> and Prieſt of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62994:6"/>the moſt high God; and of <hi>Eli</hi> and <hi>Samuel,</hi> who were both Prieſts and Judges in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> The anſwering and clearing of this will make for the advantage of the truth, and therefore I put it in the number of my Arguments. Theſe inſtances may be of ſome weight to make one think that the thing in it ſelf is not ſimply, univerſally, and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely unlawful. But what if I ſhall ſay, that theſe be caſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, and will not warrant an ordinary and general practice? That <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> was a perſon extraordinary, a ſpecial and ſingular Type of Chriſt, is clear from <hi>Pſal</hi> 110.4. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7 17. <hi>Cuneus de republicâ Judaeor,</hi> to my remembrance, holds him to be Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: but that is thought to be an error by moſt. Certain it is, he was a great man, great I mean in the ſight of God as well as great before men; For he bleſſed <hi>Abraham</hi> [the Father of the faithful] <hi>and without contradiction,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>the leſs is bleſſed of the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Heb</hi> 7.6, 7. Moreover in thoſe times the Church was much confined to Families; and the Head of the Family was both Prieſt and Governor of the Family. <hi>Job</hi> ſanctified his Sons, and offered burnt-offerings for them, <hi>Job</hi> 1.5. <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> were Prieſts, and Parents, and Magiſtrates in their Families, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their Houſholds: For if a murder had been done in any of their families, they were bound by Gods Law, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.6, to execute ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance upon the murderer.</p>
            <p>And as for <hi>Eli</hi> and <hi>Samuel,</hi> they were both Prieſts and Judges: Now Judges in thoſe times were a peculiar and extraordinary ſort of Magiſtrates and Commonwealth Governors raiſed up by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and ſometimes there was none. His Office was neither elective nor ſucceſſive; when he died, his Office died with him. When the order of Kings was inſtituted and took place in <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> the government by Judges ceaſed. Now to argue from theſe extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary and rare caſes, to an ordinary practice, I ſuppoſe will not hold.</p>
            <p>Beſides, thoſe times and ours do very much differ as to many things pertaining to Church-matters. Every Parent among the <hi>Jews,</hi> by the Law, I ſuppoſe, was to circumciſe his Male-children, <hi>Exod</hi> 4.24, 25, 26. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.10. But under the Goſpel it is made a part of the office of Paſtors to Baptize Children; and for Parents to do it, is a ſacrilegious invaſion. Under the Law all their Miniſters were cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen out of one tribe, the Tribe of <hi>Levi:</hi> It is not ſo under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel. The <hi>Jews</hi> Commonwealth was a Theocricy, it was Divine and from God: not only their Church-laws and inſtitutions, but even their political, judicial, and civil ſtatutes and ſanctions were from
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62994:6"/>God. And it was the ſame thing or office among them, to be a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and a Lawyer; to declare what was Religion and Divinity, and what was law and right between party and party. And thence it was that the High Prieſt and other inferior Prieſts and Levites were made not coercive and revenging Judges and Magiſtrates, <hi>Deut.</hi> 16.18. <hi>Ezra</hi> 7.25, but a ſort of ſpiritual Lawyers and Caſuits, to teach the people what was Law, right and wrong, and to decide in caſes and queſtions concerning matters Eccleſiaſtical, and Civil right, as ſeems evident from <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.8, 9, 10, 11, 12. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11. In thoſe times it was counted for a hainous crime for any man to invade the Prieſts Office. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah</hi> for putting his hand to uphold the Ark when the Oxen ſhook it, was ſmitten dead. And King <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah</hi> for attempting to burn Incenſe in the Temple, which was not lawful for any but the Prieſts to do, was withſtood by four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore valient men who were Prieſts, and the Lord ſmote him with Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie for his inſolency, and he continued a Leper to the day of his death, living in a ſeveral houſe. And I think it cannot be proved that it was ordinary with Gods people then to make Magiſtrates Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and Miniſters Magiſtrates; but theſe Offices were kept di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct and intire, and no man ordinarily was entruſted with both.</p>
            <p>I do further add, That thoſe Laws and Cuſtoms of the <hi>Jews,</hi> they do no further oblige Chriſtian people, than they are ſignificative of the Law of Nature; and ſo are Laws univerſal founded in natural equity, and are laws and rules of perpetual order and obſervance. <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile</hi> by the coming of Chriſt are made one. The <hi>Jews</hi> Temple, Commonwealth, Church-rites and Inſtitutions, are ceaſed, expired, and an end is put to them. There is a new miniſtration come in, and ſubſtituted in their room, more glorious and excellent, more proper for, and ſuited to the Church univerſal, conſiſting of <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi> of Nations, and People, and Languages throughout the World. There is now but one Law, and that is the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Chriſtianity; which is not two, but one entire Law or way of governing mankind under Jeſus Chriſt, ſupream under God in Heaven and in Earth, and who himſelf alſo is God: By Kings and Princes, as ſupream; and ſubordinate-Rulers and Magiſtrates under them; and by Chriſtian Paſtors, Guides and Biſhops of Souls, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates to do what is pertaining to their Office and no more; Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors alſo to do what pertaineth to their Office, and no more.</p>
            <p>Beſides, the <hi>Jews</hi> having their judicial and political Laws ſhortly and compendiouſly framed into one body by God himſelf, it was no
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62994:7"/>diſtraction to the Prieſts and Clergy then to ſtudy thoſe Laws as a part of their Divinity, and become able to decide in Cauſes and Queſtions of civil Right and Judicature. But with us of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the ſtudy of the Law is become very laborious, ſome are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſay, <hi>Frius vitiis laboravimus, nunc legibus.</hi> A man cannot be a good Judge, Chancellour, nor Juſtice of Peace, nor bear any conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Office in the Common-wealth, without inſight into the Law, the Statute Law, which is a vaſt body of Laws; and every Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is adding new ones, and the Common-Law and Cuſtoms of the Realm, and of p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rticular Courts and Places, the knowledg whereof cannot be attained with little pains, and time, and ſtudy, and without ſome experience. We have Inns of Court among us. It is made a diſtinct profeſſion and order of men among us, to be men skill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in the Law. The Laws and Cuſtoms of <hi>England</hi> are ſo intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate and hard to be well known, that it would be a great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to a Divine to give himſelf to thoſe Studies; and when he has done, he might perhaps attain to ſome ſcraps and pieces to make him a <hi>Sciolus,</hi> a Novice therein, ſo much as might ſerve him for his own private uſe; but hardly could he attain to ſo much, as to make him ripe, and judicious, and knowing enough to be a Judg or Magiſtrate. <hi>And ignorantia Judicis eſt calamitas innocentis.</hi> An ignorant Judge or Magiſtrate cannot but do much wrong, and pervert judgment for want of knowledg. A Lawyer may far better be a Divine, than a Divine can be a Lawyer. Indeed, no man can be a good Divine or Lawyer, that is not a good Chriſtian and learned in the Laws of God, the Law of Nature, and Chriſtianity, what it is to be under Law to God, and live under his Government. To be a right Divine, is to be a heavenly Lawyer. But this a man may be, and be ignorant of a thouſand quirks, and points, and matters in the Laws and Cuſtoms of <hi>England.</hi> They are ſo many, and ſo intricate, and ſo uncertain, and ſo out of the road of Divinity, and the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg and ſtudy of univerſal right, that it would be againſt conſcience and faithfulneſs in a Miniſter to give himſelf to the ſtudy of them: and without giving himſelf to the ſtudy of them, he cannot attain to the knowledg of them, competent for an Engliſh Judg and Political Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate.</p>
            <p n="14">14. <hi>Arg.</hi> 7. There are able men enough to be Judges and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates; but there is a great defect of Miniſters, and therefore it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conſiſt with wiſdom and expediency, that, I ſay, not with conſcience and honeſty, to rob the Church to make the State and Commonwealth:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62994:7"/>luxuriate. That there are able men enough to be Judges and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, and to ſerve in all offices of the Commonwealth, is either true, or it is ſome reproach to the Nobles, Gentry, and Commons of <hi>England.</hi> Cannot you do all the offices of the Common-wealth, ſerve as Magiſtrates, Judges and Rulers, and bear the Sword, and ſee to the common peace and quiet of the Nation, having the direction, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and endeavours of Paſtours both in publick and private, as Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours and no more, unleſs withall, Paſtours be made Judges and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rates too, and come into your aid? Surely then you are a degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate ſeed, you are not Chriſtian Nobles, Gentry and Commons. Let us pray for you, and pity you. If there be able men enough to bear the Sword and ſerve in all offices of the Common-wealth, why ſhould Miniſters, Biſhops and Clergy-men be called from their employments and ſpiritual function, when there is an unobſerved want of Miniſters throughout all the Nation? The work of a Biſhop, Miniſter and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtour of Souls, is to do all the ordinary Lords day work in publick, which to do well and ſubſtantially, will take up no ſmall part of his chiefeſt time, thoughts and pains. But this is not all, nor near all of his work; for he is to watch over every Soul:<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.1, 2. Acts 20.28, 31. Col. 1.28. 2 Theſ. 2.11. Gen. 31.40: Act. 15.6. Mat. 18.17.</note> he is perſonally to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct, and catechiſe, and confer with all of his charge; he is to viſit the ſick; he is to admoniſh, reprove, comfort, counſel, warn and charge every one night and day, with tears, as a Father his Children: he is to aſſiſt in neighbour-meetings and Church-aſſociations of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors and Brethren, for concord and communion; he is to hear all ſuch<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Cauſes, as need due and regular diſcipline. And is any one man able to do all this, as it ſhould be done, to any of thoſe Pariſhes in City o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Country which abound with multitudes of Souls, that would find work for many Minſters to do it faithfully, as it ſhould be done? Whereas if there be one in a Pariſh; and in ſome, one with a Reader, or Curate, that is thought, enough. I confeſs at that rate, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny do the work of the Miniſtry, it is an eaſie matter for one man to be a Paſtour to a Pariſh of a dozen Miles compaſs in the Countrey, and St. <hi>Giles</hi>'s in the <hi>Fields,</hi> St. <hi>Martins, Stepney,</hi> and <hi>Cripple-gate</hi> in the City of <hi>London.</hi> But to do the work of a Paſtour faithfully and entirely to all the Souls within any one of theſe, and ſuch like Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes, would require a whole Colledg and combination of Miniſters. We ſee in a Troop of Horſe, of but ſome fourty or fifty men, there is a Captain and a Lieutenant, beſides other Officers. In a Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Fifteen hundred, much more of fifteen thouſand, what a vaſt number of Officers are there! <hi>Captains over thouſands, Captains
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62994:8"/>over hundreds, Captains over fifties, and Captains <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> tens,</hi> Deut. 1. 15. Every tenth man was to have a Captain or Officer. But there is many a Pariſh in <hi>England</hi> that may have Ten thouſand Souls in it: and but one or two Paſtours appointed to look to all theſe fouls: When King <hi>Solomon</hi> built his Temple, <hi>He ſet threeſcore and ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand to be bearers of burdens, and fourſcore thouſand to be hewers in the mountains, and three thouſand and ſix hundred to be overſeers, to ſet the people a work,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 2.18. But in the building of the Lords ſpiritual Temple there is not one Paſtour to a thouſand Souls in many Pariſhes of <hi>England</hi> I know many will think there are too many Miniſters. I think there are to many bad ones; but I never read or heard of any Kingdom, or place, or people, to this day, that had too many faithful Miniſters: And I ſhall think it a holy and happy time when ſuch a thing is; but I deſpair to ſee it in this world. Were it not that there are not Miniſters enough to do all the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoral work of each Congregation, I ſhould think moſt of the godly Miniſters in <hi>England</hi> notoriouſly guilty before God, of groſs neglect and unfaithfulneſs, for want of perſonal and private overſight of all their people; though I think a great deal more might be done by many, than ordinarily is.</p>
            <p>Well then, there being ſo great a want of Miniſters, and no want of Magiſtrates, would you have Miniſters to turn Magiſtrates too? muſt thoſe few that are, be hindered and diſtracted, by calling them off to worldly and ſecular buſineſſes? Is it not enough that Miniſters have more work upon their hands than they can do? and would you make them more, and that too diverting and alien work <hi>extra.</hi> Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal, and almoſt, if not altogether pragmatical work? What is this but to ſerve Satan in the name of Chriſt, and under pretence of Order to pull down Order, and make the Church more low and weak by much than it is? The holy Apoſtles of our Lord were of another mind; when they ſaw they could not both look to the corporal ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities of the poor, and the ſpiritual neceſſities of Souls too, they contrived an expedient for both: They appointed a new office of Deacons in the Church, to ſee to the bodily neceſſities of the poor; but ſay they, <hi>We will give our ſelves continually to prayer, and to the miniſtry of Gods word,</hi> Act. 6.2, 4. Far unlike to thoſe that leave the Word of God and Prayer, and give themſelves to the doing of worldly matters, and ſecular buſineſſes, and teach men ſo, and plead for it as their priviledg, and a means of advantaging the Church, and of promoting holineſs and peace. <hi>Non tali auxilis, nec defenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus iſtis</hi>—<hi>tempus eget.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:62994:8"/> 15. <hi>Arg.</hi> 8. Thoſe who maintain it to be good to have Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men armed with ſecular juriſdiction, do urge for reaſon, the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the ancient Biſhops and Churches for the firſt three hundred years, while the Church was without Chriſtian Princes and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates. It was uſual in thoſe times, for the people to refer their diſſentions about worldly things to the deciſion and arbitration of their Biſhops, who to prevent going to Law before Heathen Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, and to prevent and compoſe differences and ſtrifes, and keep peace among their people, would give themſelves the trouble to hear and arbitrate Cauſes, and Pleas, and worldly differences refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to them. And hence it is argued, that if it was lawful for Clergy-men to be Arbitrators and elected Judges, to decide between brethren, it is lawful for Clergy-men to be Judges, made and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by authority, and commiſſion from the higer powers.</p>
            <p n="16">16. As to this, I take it to be true as to matter of fact, that it was uſual for the Biſhops of thoſe times to hear and arbitrate civil Cauſes and Rights: And it grew by occaſion, I was a ſaying by a miſconſtruction of the Apoſtles words, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.5, <hi>I ſpeak to your ſhame, Is it ſo, that there is not a wiſe man amongſt you? no, not one that ſhall be able to judge between his brethren?</hi> Thinking none more wiſe, and conſequently more fit to arbitrate and decide their Cauſes, than their Biſhops. And this continuing to the time of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> and he finding them in poſſeſſion thereof, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it to them, and confirmed it in their hands by Law; which was the beginning of Clergy-mens lordlineſs and domination, the fruits and conſequents whereof have been very calamitous to the Church ever ſince.</p>
            <p n="17">17. I have many things to ſay as to this: As 1. That it is very likely the ancient Biſhops who took upon them this trouble of hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and arbitrating the civil Rights and Cauſes of their people, did it with no joy, they were not fond of it, they thought it a burden, and if they might have had their choice, would rather have been free from all ſuch trouble. So much is intimated in a paſſage, which <hi>Davenant</hi> in his <hi>Determ, queſt.</hi> 11. aforenamed, quoteth out of <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> They did not eſteem them priviledges or eaſements, but <hi>moleſtias;</hi> for ſo are <hi>Auguſtines</hi> words as cited, moleſtations and troubles. But the Biſhops and Clergy of our times ſeek them, contend for them, and are tenacious of ſuch things as priviledges.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Either the Biſhops imployed in the hearing and arbitrating thoſe Cauſes, were the ſame with our Dioceſan Biſhop, or they were
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62994:9"/>not. If they were, then what diſcretion could there be in the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to refer all the Cauſes within the Biſhops Dioceſs, ſuppoſing it to be of the ſame extent and bigneſs with the Dioceſſes of Biſhops in <hi>England,</hi> to one man their Biſhop? And what diſcretion could it be in ſuch a Biſhop, as among us, the Biſhop of <hi>Norwich,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln, &amp;c.</hi> to take upon him the trouble of hearing and arbitrating all Civil cauſes, controverſies, and differences of the people inhabiting ſo vaſt a compaſs as his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſs? He muſt do nothing elſe but meerly hear civil Cauſes. He muſt be but a Biſhop in name. How expenſive, and very inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient would it be, for all the Chriſtians in any the leaſt Dioceſs in <hi>England,</hi> much more in the greateſt, to travel with their Law-Suits to the Biſhop of the Dioceſs? His Houſe then muſt be a meer <hi>Weſtminſter hall</hi> and all the days in the year, ſcarce the Lords-day excepted, muſt be term-time with him. To think that the Apoſtle ever meant any ſuch thing, when he counſels them to refer their matters to a wiſe Arbitrator, is a groſs wreſting of his words: For he wrote to the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> which was but one parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church. <hi>Is there not a wiſe man among you?</hi> He muſt be a wiſe man <hi>among them,</hi> one near at hand, eaſie to be reſorted to, to whom they might refer their Cauſes. And therefore it could not be, that the Chriſtians then referred their Cauſes to a Dioceſan Biſhop, ſuch as ours.</p>
            <p>And if not, then the Cauſe of our Dioceſan Biſhops will receive a deep wound, and it will make way for an unwelcome truth, That the Biſhops to whom the people referred their Cauſes, were the Paſtors of every Pariſh, the very ſame with our Pariſh-Miniſters, and the Rectors of Parſonages. Theſe of the Clergy were the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt to arbitrate the Cauſes of all the people within their Pariſh. A Pariſh-Biſhop or Miniſter may with far more eaſe arbitrate and compoſe the diſſentions and ſuits of all in his Pariſh, than the Dioceſan Biſhop can do of all the Paſtors and people in his Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is not the intent and meaning of the foreſaid words of the Apoſtle, that Paſtors ſhould be imployed in hearing and arbitrating the ſecular Cauſes of their own, people, or of the people of other Pariſhes. I will not ſay it is abſolutely and univerſally unlawful; nor will I ſay it is expedient in no caſe at all. There may be Caſes rarely here and there in Pariſhes, ſo circumſtanced, both under Chriſtian and Pagan Magiſtrates, in which it may be both
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62994:9"/>lawful and expedient for the Paſtors to arbitrate and compoſe ſuits and differences among the people. But generally and for the moſt part it is inexpedient. For either he will do right, or do wrong. If he do right, it is well if one ſide be not diſpleaſed, and fall out with him, and take a grudge againſt him, and either turn from him and not hear him, or hear him with prejudice; and ſo by this means the Paſtor may be an occaſion of much ſin and damage, and damnation to his Soul, which prudence, and piety, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion in a Miniſter, doth forbid, and will make him watch againſt. If he do wrong, then it is hurtful to his own Soul, it is a wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Innocent, and a perverting of Juſtice, and a ſcandal to his Miniſtry.</p>
            <p>Beſides, He can ſcarce do it but with diſtraction: If he do it but a little, it will be a hindrance to his other work, and diſtract him; much more will it hinder and diſtract him if he ſhould uſe it, and do it frequently. And the words of Chriſt are conſiderable, and worthy to be thought or, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.14, <hi>Man, who made me a judge, or a divider</hi> [an Arbitrator] <hi>between you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The words of the Apoſtle may be well underſtood in this ſenſe; either there is beſides your Paſtor a wiſe man among you, and one that is able to judge between brethren, or there is not. If there be, refer your contentions and civil cauſes to him. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther go to Law before the unbelievers, nor do you trouble your Paſtors and Biſhops; but ſingle out a wiſe man among you, one that is able to hear and decide your Cauſes, and make him Judge and Arbitrator between you. If there be not one ſuch wiſe and able man among you, then it is a ſhame and reproach to you all. What? Do you call your ſelves Saints? Do you not know that the Saints ſhall judge the world, even Angels themſelves? Are they no then fit to judge on earth ſmall matters, and to decide a petty controverſie about <hi>mine</hi> and <hi>thine</hi> between Brethren, but Brother goeth to Law with Brother, and that before the unbelievers? This is to your ſhame.</p>
            <p n="5">5. When <hi>Conſtantine</hi> came to the Crown, and Magiſtrates became Chriſtians, the moſt expedient way had been to have eaſed Paſtors of all thoſe moleſtations and avocations, and leſt the Paſtor nothing to do but his own part, and the Magiſtrate his part. To make the Clergy worldly Judges and Magiſtrates, is no benefit, but a burden<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it is nothing that a wiſe man ſhould rejoice in, but rather groan under, as a preſſure and hindrance, and pray to God to be eaſed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62994:10"/>of it, and rejoyce in being free from it, and at liberty to imploy all the time which was wont to be ſpent in ſuch Secular affairs, in Religious and Sacred exerciſes, which have a more ſpecial tenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to Souls good, and are moſt becoming a Paſtor.</p>
            <p n="18">18. Laſtly, I will ſet the worthy <hi>Davenant</hi> againſt himſelf, who going about to prove that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> hath no temporal power over Kings, lays down this poſition, — <hi>Bonum ſpirituale non poſtulat, ut ulla temporalis poteſtas a Romano pontifice exerceatur.</hi> (And if not by him, then by no other Biſhop or Paſtor whatſoever) <hi>Non eſt enim in ordine ad hunc finem, aut neceſſarium medium, aut accommodatum, aut licitum, aut denique cum ſpirituali cenſura ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicationis ullo jure connexum. Spiritual good doth not require that any temporal power be exerciſed by the Biſhop of</hi> Rome; <hi>for it is not in order to this end, either a neceſſary mean, or fit, or lawful, or laſtly by any right knit with the ſpiritual cenſure of excommunication. Determ. queſt.</hi> 4. And he gives very ſubſtantial proofs. I am at a loſs how to reconcile him to himſelf. But whether he be conſiſtent to himſelf or not, I lay not my cauſe upon that, the other proofs and evidences do overpower my underſtanding.</p>
            <p n="19">19 Now if it be manifeſtly inexpedient to make Clergy-men Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, and grant them civil juriſdiction, then it muſt needs be manifeſtly inexpedient to make them ſupream Magiſtrates, and to confer upon them the higheſt juriſdiction which Subjects be capable of, as to be Lords in Parliament, and to have equal votes with the Peers and Nobility of the Realm, and ſit as Princes there, to be many days, and weeks, and months from their Flock, and to be all that while taken up in State-matters, Civil and Secular affairs. If the other Arguments be good againſt granting any temporal authority and juriſdiction at all to Paſtors and Cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rgy men, and the Reaſons for it be exceeding weak, and but ſhews and ſhadows of Reaſon; then it muſt needs be much more inconvenient to heap ſecular ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, dignities, greatneſs, preeminence and authority upon Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and betruſt them with the higheſt juriſdiction, by making them Lords in Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iament.</p>
            <p n="20">20. <hi>They that will be rich, fall into temptation, and a ſnare, and into many fooliſh and hurtful luſts, which drown men in deſtruction and perdition,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.9. It holds good moſt ſtrongly of thoſe that ſeek both worldly wealth, and outward height, grandure and ſtate; that would be great, and ſit in the higheſt Seat, and be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Lords and Princes, and have dominion over the lives, the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62994:10"/>liberties, the eſtates, yea, and ſouls of men, and would have wealth and riches to ſupport their grandure and preferment. It is this which hath let many evils into the Church, and given occaſion to the <hi>Roman</hi>-Biſhop to lift up himſelf above all other Biſhops, yea, above Kings and Emperors themſelves, and to aſſume the title of Univerſal Biſhop, and Chriſts Vicar-general upon earth, and to uſurp authority, dominion, and ſupremacy <hi>above all that is called God,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.4. <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Chriſtian Emperor thought he did the Church a kindneſs in heaping Civil honours upon Clergy men, and putting them into places of ſtate and preferment; but in truth he did them and the Church no kindneſs. It had been well for the Church of God that Biſhops and Clergy-men had continued meer Biſhops and Clergy-men, without any worldly honours, preferments in Parliament, outward greatneſs and juriſdiction.</p>
            <p n="21">21. Nor is there any hope that the Church of God ſhould enjoy true reſt, and be ſetled in happy and laſting concord, and flouriſh as it ſhould in holineſs and Peace, till its Biſhops and Paſtors be redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to the Primitive and Apoſtolick pattern. One would think the words of our Saviour were plain enough in this caſe, when there was a ſtrife among the Twelve Apoſtles which ſhould be greateſt, our Saviour quickly ends the controverſie, by telling them, <hi>The Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Gentiles exerciſe dominion over them, and they that are great, exerciſe authority upon them. But it ſhall not be ſo among you; but whoſoever will be great and chief among you, let him be l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>weſt and ſervant of all, Mat.</hi> 20.25, 26, 27. <hi>Luk</hi> 22.25, 26. <hi>It ſhall not be ſo among you,</hi> and conſequently it ſhall not be ſo among your ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours. But ſo it hath been, and ſo it is to this day: God grant it may be ſo no longer. There is a ſtriving which ſhall be high and great, ſtriving for worldly honours, preferment, and votes and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in Parliament: There is not a ſtriving who ſhall be moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and ſelf-denying, and do the work of God faithfully. There is a ſtriving who ſhall be like the Pope, rather than Jeſus Chriſt; who ſhall have worldly lordſhip, wealth and preferment, and exerciſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination; not who ſhall be moſt good and holy, moſt faithful and diligent in the work of the Miniſtry.</p>
            <p n="22">22. Ambition and domination is not good in any; but it is worſt and moſt odious in Biſhops and Clergy-men. By ſeeking themſelves and their own honour rather than the honour of God, they loſe themſelves, and do but prepare themſelves for a fall. Is it not a moſt ſad thing to read in Church-hiſtory the contentions and ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62994:11"/>of Biſhops, and Patriarchs, and Clergy-men, about names, and places, and dignities, and worldly greatneſs, and authority; and all the doleful evils which Clergy-domination and worldly-Prelacy hath produced? And to ſee Chriſtian Emperors, Kings, Princes, States and Parliaments, to enſlave themſelves to a dominating Clergy? This is it which makes wiſe and good men to think it were much better to let Biſhops and Clergy-men be meer and ſimple Biſhops and Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy-men, and no more; and for the Magiſtrate to keep the Sword in his own hands. For if once you take up this for a principle, that the example of Chriſt and of his Apoſtles, and of the Paſtors and Biſhops of the Churches for the firſt Three hundred years, is not a ſufficient pattern, yea, and the very beſt pattern for all Chriſtian Paſtors and Churches to conform to; if once you leave this, you depart from the ſimplicity that is in Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.3. It is not poſſible to keep out pride, contention and domination, theſe will be, and they will prove the ſcab, yea the plague of the Church, and danger to eat out its vitals, or ſo weaken and conſume it, that it will want much of its ſtrength and beauty.</p>
            <p n="23">23. Sound prudence is always to go by a ſure and ſtedfaſt Rule. Chriſts pattern, the way and practice of the Apoſtles, and firſt and moſt pure Churches, is a ſure rule to go by: Keep to this, and we are ſafe. God will not find fault with us for holding us to his Rules, and ſeeking to be no more wiſe, no more holy, no more great, and honourable, and good than his Rule and Standard requires. But if you alter your rule, and once think, and ſay, the Clergy muſt have ſome more honour and juriſdiction than ſo, you let in confuſion, contention, domination, and a troop of evils and miſchiefs not to be told. As in the caſe of Ceremonies, and namely that of the Croſs in Baptiſm, if it be prudent and adviſable to add unto Gods inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Baptiſm a dedicating ſymbolical ſign, and ſay, that Baptiſm without it is not beſt as Chriſt ordained it, you may by the ſame reaſon add Cream, and Salt, and Spittle, and a multitude of vain and fooliſh things; no juſt bounds can be ſet.</p>
            <p n="24">24. And therefore Biſhops, Paſtors, and Clergy-men in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſhould make their humble addreſs to the King, the Nobility, and Commons in Parliament to this effect. — Our office is to be Biſhops and Shepherds of Souls, to give our ſelves continually to Prayer, and to the miniſtry of the Word, and to take heed to our ſelves, and to all the flock over which the Holy-Ghoſt hath made us overſeers. Had we more time than we have, had we more wiſdom
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62994:11"/>and goodneſs in our Souls, could every one of us do the work of ten of the beſt, and ableſt, and moſt godly Biſhops and Paſtors that ever the Church of God had, the Souls in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales</hi> would find us all work enough. We may not leave our work and calling unto which we are ſeparated, without injuring you, and us, and the ſouls of our people, and procuring far more damage to all ſides, than the benefit can countervail. Theſe honours that you put upon us, theſe places of dignity and juriſdiction that you put us in, are a ſnare and a burden to us: they are no priviledg but a let. To ſtrive for them, were to ſtrive to bring Fire and Gun-powder to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. All the while we be here, we tread as upon Coals of Fire. We are as if we were upon a high towring Steeple, or the t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p of a Pinacle, we cannot look upward, nor downward, behind u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, nor before us, nor on either hand, but we be in extream fear of falling. For Gods ſake, for your own ſake, for the Churches ſake, eaſe us of theſe burdens, deliver us from theſe ſnares, let us not be pragmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and buſie-bodies; you do not love to hear Divines pragmatical in the Pulpit; and why ſhould it pleaſe you, or us, to be pragmatical out of the Pulpit? We thank you for your love and well-meaning zeal; but you would not have us undone by you, and Church and State ſuffer by us, and by our ſtanding for worldly honours and preferment. We had rather be pure and ſimple Biſhops and Clergy-men, than neither pure Clergy men, nor pure Lay-men, but mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grels between both: ſimple bodies are the moſt ſolid and compact. Gold and Silver mixt, is not ſo pure and firm as pure Gold. We had rather be ſimple followers of Chriſt, and <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> and the firſt and moſt ancient Biſhops, than any thing that man can make us. Never fear that we ſhall want honour, countenance, reverence and due maintenance, while we our ſelves fulfil our name and place, and there are men and Chriſtians among us. If we want any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward deſirable reputation, eſteem, or conveniency, God will be to us an alſufficient good, and our very wants will be ſanctified to our good. Let us go to our flocks and ſeveral charges whence we came, hinder us not. Let us not be advanced in wealth, in honour, in preferment above the reſt of our brethren, who be equal with us in wiſdom, holineſs and induſtriouſneſs; and many of them do exceed us. We had rather dye preaching, and praying, and viſiting, and inſtructing the ſouls of our people, than dye voting in Parliament, and agitating State matters there. If <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou need our advice at any time in things pertaining to the Church, and which come within the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62994:12"/>ſphere and compaſs of our calling, we are ready night and day to do the beſt ſervice we can. And we deſire you will not look upon us as a divided party from the reſt of our Brethren and Proteſtant Divines in the Nation, but that you will in all your conſultations about Church-affairs, uſe the advice of the moſt ſound, and holy, and impartial, and prudent, and experienced Divines in all the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and by all means poſſible, keep the Sword and coercive power out of the hands of ſuch as be proud and lordly, and uſurp over their Brethren, and would ſet us all on a flame, and are plain world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, hypocritical, ſelf-ſeeking men, and rather Papiſts and Infidels in heart, than ſincere Chriſtians and Proteſtants. You need conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with Divines for your Souls, as you do with Lawyers for your Eſtates, and Phyſicians for your Bodies: But as you can make due uſe of Lawyers and Phyſicians, by adviſing and conſulting with them in all neceſſary caſes, without making them Stateſmen, and Peers, and Lords in Parliament, and loading them with ſecular great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, honour and juriſdiction; ſo you may make all due and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful uſe of us, as Biſhops, ſpiritual Paſtors, and Caſuiſts in Gods Church, by uſing our advice and conſultation when there is need, without loading us with worldly honours, and making us Stateſmen, and Peers, and Lords of the Realm, and Lords and Law-makers in Parliament; ſuch things be <hi>extra-epiſcopal:</hi> They will be ſmall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and comfort to us when we come to dye, and give up our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts to God. Bend your endeavours to unite all Proteſtants, and to ſtrengthen the common cauſe of Chriſtianity, Faith and Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, againſt the reigning errors and vices of the times, and the moſt malignant diſtempers of mankind, now degenerate, and far departed from God. If you find us ſuch as we ſhould not be, do right and juſtice, and let no mans crimes go unpuniſhed, nor any ſcandal lye upon the Churches, by any perſon or party whomſoever. Fidelity to God, to you, to our own ſouls, and to the Church, compels us to make this addreſs, and to quit our hands of all ſuch matters as will not ſtand with ſound prudence and integrity. The firſt and beſt part of wiſdom is not to err and do amiſs; for then there will need no repentance: but having erred, the next and only wiſdom is to repent and reform, that God may forgive us, and men may have forgiving goodneſs and charity in their breaſts towards us.</p>
            <p n="25">25. In caſe Biſhops and Clergy men ſhall ſtand for their worldly dignities and places in Parliament, and plead preſcription, and the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62994:12"/>example of their anceſtors, and the right of their ſucceſſors, and think it hard meaſure to be reformed, the Soveraign with the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and Commons in Parliament ſhould ſay to them, We are Gods Miniſters, bearing the Sword, and are to be a terrour to evil doers, and a defence to them that do well. We are to correct all diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and abuſes. <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject to the higher powers.</hi> If we find you to be out of your place and calling, we are to take cognizance thereof, and <hi>ſee that Archippus take heed to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry which he hath received in the Lord, that he fulfil it, Col.</hi> 4.17. As we may not forbear to uſe your advice and conſultation both publick and private when there is cauſe; ſo neither may we call you to counſel and conſultation needleſly, and avocate you from your Studies, and Epiſcopal and Paſtoral work, in Prayer, and Preaching, and Overſeeing your ſeveral flocks, without cauſe: unto you belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the power of the Word and Keys, unto us belongeth the power of the Sword. If you ſee any miſdemeanours in us, do your duty faithfully, kill us not by kindneſs, flatter us not to our ruine, make utmoſt uſe of that authority God hath given you in his Church to edification, conceal nothing from us and the people which is godly and profitable for us to know; ſpare to reprove no ſin which is a ſin, and which needs reproving; do your duty faithfully, be pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, be pious, be peaceable, be diligent and blameleſs in your place, and we ſhall defend you, and be a terrour to all that would harm and oppoſe you. But if it will not content you to be as <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> and the holy Biſhops and Paſtors of old, but you will needs be uſurping the Magiſtracy, and ſeeking domination, and make your Brethren of the Clergy your underlings; if you will needs be prag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical and buſie-bodies, and neglect the work of Prayer and Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſuffer the ſouls of your people to want due overſight and paſtoral care; if you will beat your fellow-ſervants, and cauſeleſly fall out with your Brethren and the univerſal Church, we muſt not wink at ſuch offences, but declare, them to be crimes puniſhable by a lawful Magiſtracy, which we are, under God. We will hear of no plea or preſcription againſt Piety, Prudence and Peace. Uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, domination, paſtoral negligence, and unfaithfulneſs, and groſs imprudencies, are not priviledges, but ſins and crimes: to ſay they are ancient, is to ſay they are more odious, and call for the more deep repentance, and ſpeedy, and ſound, and through reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="26">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:62994:13"/> 26. There are in this, as in moſt other caſes, two extreams, which be alike equi-diſtant from the true and right mean. The one is to make no uſe at all of Divines, nor to conſult with them in any caſe. This I take to be a dangerous extream, contrary to the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the true office and inſtitution of the Miniſtry, and that duty which all Chriſtian Princes, and Parliaments, and People do owe to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; unto whom they are vowed and ſworn to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve his Laws, and to be ſincerely ſubject to his government in all things. And he doth govern his Church by Paſtors, Teachers, and ſpiritual Overſeers, with whom all perſons of what degree and rank ſoever they be, are to adviſe and conſult, not in every ſmall and little matter, but in caſes of weight and concernment, if they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not otherwiſe ſatisfie themſelves; as they will do with Lawyers about their Eſtates, and Phyſicians about their Bodies. The Papiſts do groſly tyrannize over all, both Kings and Subjects, by binding them to make a particular recitation or confeſſion of their ſins to their Prieſts, at certain times frequently; thereby making themſelves Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in ſome ſort of mens conſciences, and unjuſtly privy to their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, and abuſing the name, authority, and ordinance of Chriſt, to rigour and tyranny, and thereby deceiving and deluding ſouls in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to much ſuperſtition, vaſſalage, and hypocriſie. To avoid which, Anti-papiſts have run into a quite contrary extream, forgetting of what daily and ſtanding uſe and concernment Gods Miniſters are, both to perſons and ſocieties. <hi>The Prieſts lips are to keep knowledg, and the people are to ſeek the Law at their mouth, Mal.</hi> 2.7.</p>
            <p>When the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> were to ſend back the Ark, they conſulted with their Prieſts and Diviners, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.2.</p>
            <p>Miniſters are not only to be heard in publick, but to be conſulted with in private, and to be made uſe of in all caſes and queſtions Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical, which concern the general intereſt of the Church, its holineſs and its unity, and which cannot well and ſoundly be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined without the aſſiſtance, advice, and direction, of impartial, wiſe and holy Divines. I am ſo far from being againſt this, that rather I judge it a common errour and miſpractice in Chriſtian States, as well as particular perſons, that they do not make that due and godly uſe of Miniſters and Divines, which they ought to do; whence it is that they do ſo often miſcarry in their ways and counſels, becauſe they do too much lean to their own underſtandings, and either con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult not at all with Gods Miniſters, or if they do, they conſult with thoſe only which are partial and unfaithful, or they do treacherouſly
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62994:13"/>and hypocritically conceal ſomething of the caſe from them, or do like the Papiſts, which make confeſſion a meer ceremony, reſting in the work done, imitating her in <hi>Prov.</hi> 7.14.</p>
            <p>People can ſend for Miniſters to adviſe with upon their ſick-beds; they ſhould do it when they are in health. There is Parliament hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility and ſelf-denial, which Jeſus Chriſt doth bind all Chriſtian States and Rulers to, <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.23. The long Parliament had their Aſſembly of Divines.</p>
            <p n="27">27. The other extream is of making more and further uſe of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters than need requires, and than will ſtand with the prudence, conveniency, and quality of their work and calling; and in making an undue diſparity and inequality among Miniſters and Divines, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing ſome to be Lords and Dominators over the reſt, advancing them too high in worldly dignities, authority and preferment, and thereby eſtabliſhing pride and partiality: It is grounded upon a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, which is, that by Gods Law, Biſhops and Arch-biſhops have a majority of power and juriſdiction above the reſt of the Paſtors, though they excel, or be equal to the Biſhops, and Arch-biſhops, in true wiſdom and holineſs, and Miniſterial graces and diligence; whereas it is evident from the very nature of the thing it ſelf, that a Biſhop and Overſeer of Souls, are but two names for the ſame thing: and that to be an Arch-biſhop, is to be <hi>Epiſcoporum primus,</hi> an eminent Presbyter, the chief of all the Biſhops, Presbyters and Paſtors: not that he hath a greater commiſſion than they. The authority and commiſſion of Biſhops, Paſtors, and Miniſters, is but one, <hi>Matt.</hi> 28.19, 20, and it conſiſteth in theſe three. 1. An au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to Chriſtianize Souls, and admit Diſciples into the Family of Chriſt, which is his Church, by Baptiſm. 2. An authority to uſe them as Diſciples and Members of the Family when admitted, by ſeeding them with knowledg and underſtanding, watching over them, and doing all neceſſary and convenient, epiſcopal and paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral acts and offices to them. 3. An authority to diſcommon and caſt out of the Family, by penal and juridicial Church-cenſures, contumacious and groſly diſorderly livers, whom no other remedies will amend.</p>
            <p n="28">28. This threefold authority every right ordained Presbyter or Pariſh Miniſter hath, and no Arch-biſhop or Biſhop hath more; for more is not neceſſary, nor is there any place for more. And leſs will not ſuffice to make a man a compleat Paſtor; and Chriſt makes no incompleat Paſtors. <hi>Qui aliquid alicui concedit, concedit
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62994:14"/>&amp; id ſine quo res ipſa nequit concedi.</hi> He that gives the end, doth includedly give the due, and regular, and ſubſervient means. And, <hi>Qui adimit medium, deſtruit finem.</hi> We muſt not for fear of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king every Paſtor a Pope, deny him to be a Paſtor. Grant him to be a Paſtor, and thereby you grant unto him paſtoral power; and then you grant him authority to caſt out as well as to take in; to have an expulſive as well a a receptive faculty. Miniſters may abuſe their authority; ſo alſo may Magiſtrates, Parents, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But is that any ground to deny them the authority of Magiſtrates and Parents? If they be not fit to be truſted with the paſtoral of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, let them not be Paſtors at all. If they be fit to be Paſtors, let them be compleat paſtors. An incompleat Paſtor is <hi>terminus diminuens.</hi> No Scripture, nor ſound Reaſon doth give any warrant for making men but half-Biſhops, half-Paſtors and Presbyters. I ſay again, That an Arch-biſhop is but an eminent Presbyter, as <hi>Peter</hi> among the Apoſtles, or as the foreman of the jury. The reſt of the Apoſtles are compleat Apoſtles as well as <hi>Peter,</hi> and have equal commiſſion and authority. The reſt of the Jury are jurors as well as the Foreman, and are equal judges of the fact. True it is, that among Apoſtles and Paſtors who be equal as to Office and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, there may be much inequality as to gifts and graces, and faithful and wiſe execution of their office. As all Parents have alike authority over their Children; but all Parents are not alike wiſe, and good, and officious in their places: unto ſome God giveth ten talents, unto ſome five, unto ſome two, unto all at leaſt one. And it is Gods will that he who is beſt, be beſt eſteemed, and that the leſs wiſe do learn of the more wiſe, that the <hi>younger ſubmit themſelves unto the elder, yea, all of you be ſubject one to another, and be clothed with humility,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.5 Miniſters cannot always be executing their Office, as Praying, Preaching, Baptizing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And there may be ſome parts and branches of the Office which they may never be called to exerciſe, as Ordination, authoritative Excommunication, and Abſolution. And no authority is given but for uſe and edification; and where there is no uſe of it, or where it cannot be uſed without making things worſe, and doing more hurt than good, it is to be forborn. But it is fit that Miniſters be Miniſters, and Paſtors and Biſhops, be Paſtors and Biſhops, and be inveſted and intruſted with compleat Paſtoral and Epiſcopal pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and that they do uſe and exerciſe every branch and part of their office and authority, when, and ſo often as ſanctified Conſcience,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62994:14"/>and ſound prudence and diſcretion ſhall ſay it is convenient, and they cannot forbear to do it without manifeſt damage and inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience; as it is convenient a Captain have his Sword, though he may not be put to uſe it in fight againſt any. And it is fit that a Schoolmaſter have power to uſe his <hi>Ferula,</hi> and moderately cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect untoward and miſruly Scholars, though poſſibly he may have none ſuch, and ſo never be put to uſe the Rod.</p>
            <p n="29">29. This being ſo, I muſt needs grant, that if it be convenient, and adviſable, that the whole tribe of Miniſters who be of the order of Presbyters, be accounted Lord-Biſhops, Lord-Presbyters, Lord-Paſtors, and Lord-Preachers, and have equal right to be Lords and Stateſmen in Parliament, and ſupream Judges in all cauſes and que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, both Political and Eccleſiaſtical, which ſhall come before that honourable Aſſembly; then I yield the cauſe, my poſition is erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous, and I do ill to ſay it is inconvenient that Clergy-men be Lords and Stateſmen in Parliament. But if it be inconvenient and againſt ſound prudence, to honour, or rather burden the whole Tribe of Miniſters, and right-ordained Paſtors and Presbyters, with theſe honours, preferments, greatneſs and authority, then I ſee not but my poſition will hold ſound and good; for if all appearance of evil is to be avoided, then all appearance of partiality is to be avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and of that partiality which hath conjoined with it many ſnares, and which a wiſe man is bound to avoid as diſtractions, precipices, and burdens. I have no envious partiality againſt Arch-biſhops and Biſhops; I am neither againſt the name, nor the office and thing imported by the name. Every Paſtor unto whom God doth give more than ordinary gifts and graces, is in my judgment a real Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop in Gods Church, <hi>jure Divino:</hi> a chief Paſtor and eminent Prelate in Gods Church above his fellows: of which rank I do eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate the famous <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher, Auguſtine, Athanaſius, Calvin, Zanchy, Bradford, Davenant, Cranmer, D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, Bains, Hilderſham, Preſton, Sibbs, Gataker, Joſeph Hall, Babington, Joſeph Allaine,</hi> and many more both ancient and modern Divines: all burning and ſhining lights in Gods Church, more eminent than vulgar Divines. I think my ſelf not worthy to carry their Books after them. I think they better deſerve the Title of Lord, than many a temporal carnal Lord that is honoured with that name. The fifth Commandment bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me to honour my Father and my Mother: and my Catechiſm teacheth me, that by Father and Mother is to be underſtand all ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors in office, age and gifts. Good <hi>Obadiah</hi> ſays to <hi>Elijah, Art
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62994:15"/>thou that my Lord Elijah,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.8? The truth is, our ordinary word <hi>Maſter,</hi> or <hi>Sir,</hi> which we give to almoſt all, importeth the ſame with the title <hi>Lord,</hi> it being in <hi>Greek, Kurios</hi> and <hi>Kurie,</hi> in <hi>Latin Dominus</hi> and <hi>Domine,</hi> ſave that cuſtom which is the great arbiter of Speech, doth appropriate this title <hi>Lord,</hi> to the temporal nobility. If we muſt give honour to whom honour is due, and honour all whom God doth honour, or elſe we are diſobedient to Gods word and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy, then both Clergy-men and Lay-men, Magiſtrates, Paſtors, Parents, and private Chriſtians are to be honoured with decent and ſeemly honour, without denying them what all wiſe and peaceable Chriſtians account to be their due, and to be ſafe and decent to be given to them; or giving them more, out of flattery and baſeneſs, having mens perſons in admiration becauſe of advantage. See <hi>Job</hi> 32.22. <hi>Jude</hi> 16.</p>
            <p n="30">30. But now it is not the cuſtom with us, nor with the Churches of Chriſt and Chriſtian people, and cuſtom in this caſe creates a Law, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16, to give the Title Lord to the Pariſh-biſhops and Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, though never ſo eminent: and it is but meet, that accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the uſe of all Nations, and the Scripture it ſelf, a difference be made between the temporal Nobility and the Clergy. And why it ſhould be given to a Popiſh Biſhop meerly becauſe a Biſhop, ſuch as <hi>Bonner, Gardiner,</hi> and many of the Popes and Cardinals, who have been wretched men, or to a <hi>Ridley,</hi> a <hi>Hooper,</hi> a <hi>Davenant,</hi> rather than to a <hi>Bradford,</hi> a <hi>Philpot,</hi> a <hi>Dod,</hi> a <hi>Joſeph Alleine,</hi> I know not. If the honour be due to the Office, then all Miniſters muſt be counted Lord-biſhops and Lord-paſtors, I am clear in that, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.1. This I know will not pleaſe our Lord Arch-Biſhops and Biſhops, and thoſe whoſe zeal upholds them. All that I contend for is, that all that be equal in office, be equal in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and no one partially preferred; no one aſſume to himſelf car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſtate and ſuperiority over his Brethren. <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.5, <hi>Behold, how great a matter a little fire kindleth!</hi> This advancing of equals above their equals, and brethren above their brethren, and paſtors above paſtors, in Gods Church, is not good.</p>
            <p n="31">31. I do not impugn bare names and titles, but my aim is to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugn factious partiality, and pride in Clergy-men, occaſioned by the over-indulgence of Princes and ſupream Magiſtrates. It is ſimplicity, humility, and ſincerity in Biſhops, which I contend for. Either the Arch-biſhops and Biſhops muſt come down, and abate of their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, their lordlineſs, their principalities and worldly ſtate, and be
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62994:15"/>upon even ground with the reſt of their Brethren, who have as good inſides as they, and are as real Biſhops and Overſeers of ſouls as they, and have equal office, authority and commiſſion with them, <hi>Matt.</hi> 28.19, 20. <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.23. and will paſs for as much at death and judgment as they: or elſe the reſt of their Brethren who be equal in office and merits to them, muſt be heightned and advanced, and made to be upon even ground with them. This latter is not adviſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, nor will be granted; it is not fit it ſhould: The other is both feiſiable and convenient. It will make our Arch-biſhops and Biſhops to be no worſe men, nor worſe Arch biſhops and Biſhops, if they be but meer and ſimple Biſhops of Souls, and meddle no more in State-matters, and ſecular affairs, than needs they muſt, and will ſtand with the order, and quality, and greatneſs of their work.</p>
            <p n="32">32. Do you think in good earneſt, that Church and State will all go to rack and ruine, if our two Arch-biſhops, and the Dioceſan Biſhops be not preſent in Parliament, and ſit as Lords and Princes there? muſt they have the hearing of every Cauſe, and be ſupream Judges and Magiſtrates, and political Officers under the King? were it not more becoming you to be among your people, Preaching and Praying, and viſiting the Souls and Families under your charge, in imitation of the Apoſtles, <hi>Act.</hi> 20. <hi>Act.</hi> 6.2, 3, 4, 21, 28, 31. than ſtriving for worldly greatneſs and ſecular precedency? Is not the way to Heaven ſtrait enough to you, but you will make it more ſtrait? cannot Traytors and Murderers be tried without you? would it be any diſparagement to the beſt of you all to be as <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l,</hi> yea, as Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, rather than like the Pope? do you ſtand for theſe worldly honours and preeminencies out of pure zeal for Gods Glory, and the Churches good? Why then do you heat your fellow-ſervants, and uſe them more unchriſtianly than Pagans have uſed Chriſtians? <hi>Act.</hi> 38.20, 21. and give your Votes that all the Paſtors in the Land be ſilenced and put down, for not aſſenting and conſenting to many things which you your ſelves confeſs to be in their own nature indifferent, all moderate and ſound conforming Miniſters confeſs to be burdenſom and inconvenient, and multitudes of conſcientious, and learned, and peaceable diſſenting Divines and Proteſtants do ſay, are flatly unlawful?</p>
            <p n="33">33. It is an errour to think that Epiſcopacy, and Arch-epiſcopacy cannot ſtand, unleſs Biſhops and Arch biſhops be made Lords, and Legiſlators, and Princes in Parliament, and have worldly grandeur, authority, and greatneſs to ſupport the ſimple office of Prelacy and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62994:16"/>Epiſcopacy in Gods Church. Theſe worldly additions and cumulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſecular office and honour, are things extrinſical to right and ſimple Prelacy and Epiſcopacy. Right and ſimple Prelacy and Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy do not ſtand by the will and donation of Princes, but by a ſuperior Law, even by Divine and unchangeable Right, by the Word of God, and by the Law and light of nature, and the intrinſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal goodneſs and expediency of the thing. For if there were no Chriſtian Magiſtracy or Parliament, yet would there be Prelacy and Epiſcopacy in Gods Church. It is of the law of Nature that the beſt be beſt eſteemed, and that vulgar Paſtors and Divines, that have but one or two talents of Miniſterial and Epiſcopal learning, holineſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, wiſdom and uſefulneſs, give place to thoſe who are more eminent, and whoſe graces and vertues do render them ſingularly excellent above their Brethren, though they have but one and the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and authority. Authority is one thing, ſpiritual and men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal qualifications and endowments are another thing. Now we ſee how that God himſelf doth difference among the Paſtors, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring on ſome, extraordinary abilities, and qualifications, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by notifying to all the Churches, the ſingular reverence and eſteem which he would have ſuch eximious perſons to have from all the Churches; as <hi>Daniel</hi> was preferred above the Preſidents, <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.3, and <hi>Eſther</hi> and her Maids above the Women, <hi>Eſther</hi> 2.9.</p>
            <p n="34">34. Every man naturally hath a Pope in his belly, is the common ſaying: Pride is an inborn ſin. It is exceſſive pride in the Pope, to think himſelf more than a man; and it is exceſſive pride in an Infant to think himſelf a grown man: and in Paſtors that be but of infant-underſtandings, to think themſelves equal with ſuch as be of grown, and large, and ſingularly eminent underſtandings.</p>
            <p>Simple Prelacy among Divines, is a Divine thing. Every eminent, holy and wiſe Presbyter, is a real Arch-biſhop in Gods Church: This he would be, were there no Chriſtian Magiſtracy to uphold him. There is a ſubjection due from one Paſtor to another, as from one man to another, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.5. As it will not ſtand with true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an humility, ſelf-denyal, and ſubjection to Chriſt in all things, that Paſtors do dominate over Paſtors, and Lord it over their Brethren, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.3: So it will not ſtand with the ſame Chriſtian graces and duties, for one Miniſter of inferior and ſmaller parts, gifts and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, not to acknowledg the greater gifts and graces of others whom God hath made more eminent.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:62994:16"/>
            <p> There is as great variety of Paſtors, as there is of Men and of Saints; ſome are as eyes, ſome as hands, ſome as feet in Gods Church. The weakeſt ſincere Chriſtian Paſtor, is a Paſtor, as truly as the higheſt and moſt excellent Paſtor, and is of uſe in his place: In this there is no difference between the moſt eminent Arch-biſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> and the meaneſt honeſt Pariſh-Miniſter. But then as to wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and holineſs, and uſefulneſs, there is great difference and ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality; and out of this ariſeth natural, ſimple, divine and unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Prelacy, Epiſcopacy and Arch-epiſcopacy; which is not a thing pleaſing to fleſh and blood, and it doth neither favour, nor make againſt any of the three forms of Church-government called Prelacy, Presbytery, and Independency; further than they do favour, or be againſt true impartial godlineſs: of which this divine and ſimple Prelacy among Divines, is one eſſential branch. I do not ſay, it is an appendant or appurtenant of Godlineſs and Religion; but is an eſſential branch. It is of the eſſence of my Religion that I put a difference, as between a godly and ungodly Paſtor; ſo alſo between a godly Paſtor, that is almoſt ungodly, and hath but one talent of godlineſs; and a godly Paſtor, who is of the higheſt rank of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Paſtors, and is full of the wiſdom, and grace, and joy of the Holy Ghoſt, and is of extraordinary uſefulneſs and eminency in Gods Church.</p>
            <p>We muſt not, for fear of inclining to the Popes lordlineſs and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, run into another dangerous extream, and tempt Infants to think they are Men, and Scholars to think that they are fit to be Teachers; and Learning Diſciples, Novices, and Children, that they are equal in wiſdom and knowledg to their Parents, Maſters and Tutors, between whom there is no compare.</p>
            <p n="35">35. I make no doubt but there have been holy and eminent men Lord-biſhops and Arch-biſhops, Peers in Parliament: God forbid that I ſhould think or ſay otherwiſe. But either they were no more but meer and ſimple Biſhops and Arch-biſhops, choſen and ſingled forth from among their Brethren, to be conſulted with in matters and caſes eccleſiaſtical, and proper for Divines and Biſhops; or they were more.</p>
            <p>If the former, and they kept in the rank and ſtation of Biſhops and Divines, for my part I am not he that ſhall oppoſe it. And if there be any word in all this diſputation againſt ſuch uſe of Biſhops and Divines, <hi>indictum volo,</hi> I wiſh it unſaid.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:62994:17"/>
            <p> But if they were more, and took themſelves to be more than ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Biſhops and Paſtors in Gods Church, and to be ſuperior to their brethren in power and authority; if they took themſelves to be ſupream Magiſtrates and Judges, under, and with the King in the Houſe of Lords, and to have juriſdiction and lordſhip proper to Magiſtrates and ſupream coercive Judges, and to the Nobility, Peers and Princes in Parliament; this I hold to be <hi>extra</hi> epiſcopal, to be a ſwerving from the ſimplicity that is in Chriſt, and an undue prelation of Paſtors above Paſtors, and a deformity added to the beauty and luſtre of ſimple Epiſcopacy; and it is a cauſe of more evil than good, and upon a juſt computation of all, both conveniences and inconveniences; it will be found a truth, that Church and State have been both loſers; that Biſhops and Arch-biſhops themſelves, who have had ſuch external honours, preeminences and authorities, have been loſers in their Souls by them, and that it had been better for all ſides, that they had kept in the ſtation and quality of ſimple Biſhops and Divines.</p>
            <p n="36">36. The Arch-biſhops and Biſhops with us have three Ordinations; firſt, they are ordained Presbyters, then they are ordained Biſhops, then they are ordained Arch-biſhops. Now theſe two laſt Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are rather nullities and corruptions, and do ſuppoſe that there is a majority and ſuperiority of power in Biſhops over Presbyters, and in Arch-biſhops over Biſhops; and the next ſtep muſt be in the Pope over all. For to be a Biſhop and Shepherd over all the Souls and Shepherds which be in <hi>England,</hi> is a vice of the very ſame kind with that of the Popes, who ſays he is Chriſts Vicar upon Earth, and Biſhop over all the Biſhops and Souls which be in the world; which is to claim and uſurp the office of Jeſus Chriſt, and to attempt the doing of that which is abſolutely impoſſible. It is indeed more impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for one man to be Biſhop and Paſtor over all the Souls and Biſhops which be in the world, than it is for one man to be Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop and Paſtor over all the Souls and Paſtors which be in <hi>England.</hi> Both be alike ſimply impoſſible, though the one is more impoſſible than the other. And they do both ſavour of proud ſelf ignorance, and groſs affectation, and ſelf-ſeeking, as though one man could be in a thouſand places at once, Baptizing, Preaching, giving the Lords-ſupper, viſiting the ſick, inſtructing ſouls, and doing all other the acts and offices of a Scripture-Biſhop and Spiritual Overſeer of Souls, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. To the creating of a Biſhop or Arch biſhop, there needs no more but an election and nomination of him to the place, as is done by the Houſe of Commons when they chuſe a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:62994:17"/>Speaker. His office is no more but to be as the Foreman of the Queſt. If he have not wiſdom, holineſs, and Miniſterial worth and uſefulneſs anſwerable to his name, he is but an Arch-biſhop in name, he is rather a poſt or cypher than a man.</p>
            <p n="37">37. Alſo our Prelates do take upon them to be Eccleſiaſtical Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlators and Canon-makers to all the Churches, and to all other Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors; and they conſtitute them a Lay-Chancellour, and require of all the Clergy an Oath or ſolemn promiſe of Canonical obedience to them and their Chancellors. They call their Chancellor their Vicar in ſpirituals, and unto him is committed the power of diſcipline and juriſdiction eccleſiaſtical over all, both Clergy and Laity; and the Church-Canons are his Law and Rule, which being too crooked for honeſt men to conform to, he ſpares not to excommunicate them; and upon a <hi>ſignificavit</hi> made by him into the <hi>Chancery,</hi> out comes an <hi>Excommunicato capiendo,</hi> and the party muſt either go to Priſon all his days without Bail, or make his compoſition much to his ſhame or damage, or both. And Excommunications and Abſolutions in the Biſhops Court are bought and ſold for money; and the worſt men are ſpared and countenanced, while the beſt men are haraſſed, and anathematized, and accurſed from Chriſt and his Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="38">38. Now the Biſhops being conſcious to themſelves, that this kind of prelacy, and domination, and juriſdiction, is not good and equal, but rather like the Popes ſupremacy over all, and thoſe whom the Holy Ghoſt brands, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 5.15, who ruled over Gods people by their Servants, as now the Biſhops do by their Vicars, Subſtitutes, and Chancellors; but ſo did not good <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> becauſe of the fear of God: They, I ſay, being ſenſible hereof, do get to be Princes, and Lords, and Stateſmen in Parliament, and thereby inſinuate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the Soveraign, and with ſuch of the Nobles and Gentry as love to be flatter'd and ſmoothly dealt with; and by this means eſtabliſh to themſelves, and to their Chancellors, worldly and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal juriſdiction, and dominate over their Brethren, and become the Authors of Sects and Factions, and hinder the holineſs, the unity and concord of the Churches, and rather than they ſhall not be Lord-biſhop, and partial, and factious, and buſie bodies in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Church and State muſt ſuffer, and the common quiet be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered. They will not endure to be upon equal ground with their Brethren as wiſe and good as themſelves: as the Pope will not abide to be touch'd in his ſupremacy.</p>
            <p n="39">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:62994:18"/> 39. I ſhall add this one word of caution, Though it be not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient that Biſhops be made Magiſtrates, and Paſtors truſted with the Sword; yet it is fit that Magiſtrates be Magiſtrates, and not Cyphers, and that they do not bear the Sword in vain; and that they do back the power and authority of the Miniſtry, and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and uphold the ſacred Office, by being a terror to evil do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and a praiſe and defence to them that do well. There ought to be a due temperament of Magiſtracy and Miniſtry, that we might lead a peaceable and quiet life in all godlineſs and honeſty. Though the Sword is not Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Ordinance for the converſion of ſouls, yet it is Gods Ordinance for the puniſhing of vice, and protection of vertue outwardly; and for the juſt encouragement of worthy Paſtors, and the diſcouragement of the unworthy. Anciently God did lead his people by the hand of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron;</hi> they both made but one hand.</p>
            <p>And it is a Law of univerſal equity, binding all Chriſtian Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealths. <hi>Judges and magiſtrates ſhalt thou make thee in all thy gates, which the Lord thy God giveth thee throughout thy tribes: and they ſhall judg thy people with juſt judgment, Deut.</hi> 16.18. And as there ought to be a ſufficient Miniſtry in every Pariſh; ſo alſo there ought to be a due proportion and contemperament of coer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cive Judges, and revenging Magiſtrates, in Cities, Towns and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes, that the people might have both Law and Goſpel; means for their Souls, and means for their outward peace and ſafety nigh at hand.</p>
            <p>It was the cuſtom in <hi>England</hi> anciently, for the Biſhop and the Sheriff, who was then called Earl of the County, and was ſupream Magiſtrate under the King in the County, to go in Circuit all over the County, the one to teach the people Religion and the way of good living, and to viſit all the Churches; and the other to decide civil Cauſes, and to chaſtiſe and correct offenders and offences, and execute revenging wrath upon evil doers: And by this means there was much quiet, and good living, and order in the Realm. This courſe is now antiquated and degenerated into another courſe, not ſo profitable and convenient for good order and publick quiet; and that is the Circuit of Judges itinerant twice each year through the Realm, keeping their Aſſizes at one place only, and making all the County to come thither: and having a Judges Sermon Preached at the entrance of the Aſſizes.</p>
            <p>Though the Church and Miniſtry will ſtand if the Paſtors do their
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:62994:18"/>duty; yet if Chriſtian Magiſtrates do not their duty in their place and calling, they do ſo far unchriſtianize themſelves; and if they protect the evil, and puniſh the good, or think that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> pretence of Liberty of Conſcience men may be allowed to blaſpheme God, to teach Atheiſm, Infidelity, and Soul-deſtroying doctrines, and ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the part of <hi>Corah</hi> and his complices, againſt the faithful Miniſters of Chriſt, God will make them know one day, that that was not the end for which he appointed them Magiſtrates, and that they be his Miniſters, and are therefore called Gods, and ought not to bear the Sword in vain, and to ſtand by, and ſee the Church waſted, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted and torn in pieces by violence, hereſies, ſchiſms, profaneneſs and wickedneſſes, and they be like <hi>Gallio,</hi> unconcerned, and care for no ſuch things.</p>
            <p>And the truth is, it is no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ttle that the due execution of the Magiſtrates office doth conduce to the ſucceſs of the Goſpel, and the promoting of the Miniſtry, and of the Word and Work of God upon mens Souls. And therefore though I diſſent from the worthy <hi>Davenant</hi> in this, That he would have Paſtors to be Magiſtrates, and I would have Paſtors to be but meer Paſtors, and the Off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce of the Magiſtrates to be an Office by it ſelf, and beſtruſted with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who are no Paſtors, and who may intend it, and make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their work: yet thus far I agree, that it is moſt convenient and godly, that throughout all the Churches, there be in every place an heir of reſtraint, a revenger to execute wrath upon them that do evil, and to protect the good; that theſe two ſtanding Ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt, and of God the Father by him, may ſtand and conſiſt together, and walk hand in hand, and mutually ſupport and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve each other for the Glory of God, and the good of Church and Common-wealth. And this is no <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>topia</hi> or Platonick Idea or form of a Common-wealth, which is but a fiction or imagination, no where to be found in this World: But it is obvious and plain to all, and needs not ſo much any new inſtitution, as a reſtauration of ancient practice, and a faithful execution of what all ſides agree in, conſiſtent with the munici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al laws and ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctions of this Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="40">40. If any ſhall think I have committed inexpediency in writing againſt inexpediency, and have medled with a point that will not abide to be medled with<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when I am convinced of it, I will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg my error: Till then, I will ſtand upon mine own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and plead not guilty. Almoſt imprudent, is prudent. If any t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>x me of pragmaticalneſs, I anſwer, it is pragmaticalneſs that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:62994:19"/>I write againſt, and I cannot cure the wound unleſs I ſearch it to the bottom, and apply to it ſuitable Plaiſters. Pragmatical Divines cannot content themſelves to be Divines in common with their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; but they will play the Biſhops in anothers Dioceſs, and think it well becomes them to immerſe themſelves in State-affairs. If it ſhall be ſaid, that hereby I caſt aſperſion upon the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Nation, and cenſure the judgment and eſteem of many generations of Princes, Parliaments, Wiſe-men, Divines and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors. I anſwer, That if it be lawful for a <hi>Davenant</hi> to aſſert in Schools, and publiſh to the world an erroneous poſition, <hi>Civilis ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdictio, jure conceditur eccleſiaſticis;</hi> it cannot be thought unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful by equal judges, for another, though not to be named with <hi>Davenant,</hi> to aſſert the contrary, and ſhew the unſoundneſs of his opinion, though with all juſt reverence to ſo worthy a man. And in doing this, I do but expound the true meaning and extent of the fifth Commandment, and aſſert the rights of the Church uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal, and the conſentient judgment of the beſt and ſoundeſt Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, and the due bounds of Magiſtracy and Miniſtry, and reduce things to primitive order and ſimplicity, according to the pattern of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and the firſt and pureſt times of the Church.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:62994:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
